小子！
(LORD UHTRED) Boy!
潮水要转了!
The tide is on the turn!
我不会再警告你第二次!
I'm not warning you again!
船!在那儿!
(OSBERT) Ships! There!
丹麦人
Danes.
魔鬼的走狗
The devil's turds.
- 他们是商人吗? - 不,他们是来劫掠的维京人!
- Are they traders? - No. They come as Vikings!
走!
We go!
走!走!
Go! Go!
抓紧!
(MAN) Hold on!
我儿子在哪?
(LORD UHTRED) Where's my son?
乌特雷德,带六个人骑马去河边
Uhtred. Take half a dozen men, ride to the river.
那里有异教徒,盯着他们，看清楚有多少人
There are pagans there. Watch them, see how many.
- 明白 - 不要多生事端
- Of course. - Do nothing more.
是,父亲
(UHTRED) Yes, Father. (GLENNA) Osbert.
- 怎么了? - 有船，我看见了
- What is it? - Ships. I saw them.
- 什么船? - 丹麦人，正朝河这边来
- What ships? - Danes. They're heading for the river.
愿天主与众圣人保佑我们,他们没有灵魂
God and his saints preserve us. They have no soul.
- 我们该祈祷 - 我们该行动
- We must pray. - We must act.
乌特雷德，不许和他们交战，一个都不行
Uhtred. Do not fight them, not a single one.
- 天黑前回来 - 是
- Be back by nightfall. - Yes.
他们是天主降下的惩罚,为了我们的罪孽
They are sent by God to punish us for our sins.
他们是来支援约克的维京军队的
They're here to support the Viking army in Eofervvic.
让神父去祈祷，求天主救我们
Instruct the priest to pray for our deliverance.
- 埃尔弗里克！ - 大人？
- Aelfric! - Lord?
- 把他们带进去 - 把妇女和老人带进来
- Get them inside. - Take in the women and elders.
其余人去高地，别让人看见
The rest to higher ground, out of sight.
召集乡民，我要这座要塞里的每一个男人
Rouse the country. I want every man in this fortress.
每个人都要做好赴死的准备
And every man must be prepared to die.
左舷准备划桨！
(MAN 1) Port side ready to row!
左舷就位！右舷准备划桨！
(MAN 2) Port side ready! (MAN 1) Starboard side ready to row!
右舷准备划桨！
(MAN 2) Starboard side ready to row!
父亲
Father.
收桨！收桨！
(MAN 1) Rest your oars! (MAN 2) Rest your oars!
尝尝
Taste.
没味道，是淡水
Bland. Fresh.
- 甜水 - 对
- Sweetwater. - Yes.
你还看到了什么？
What else do you see?
我看到一条清澈的河
EARL RAGNAR: I see a clear river,
鱼大得像人的腿一样粗
fish as big as a man's leg.
我看到树林里到处是猎物
I see a forest alive with meat.
不止如此，我看到了一个可以安享晚年的地方
More than that, I see a place to grow fat and old.
有马
Horses.
是啊，我还看到了探子
Yeah. And I see spies,
吓得裤裆都湿了
shitting themselves.
我们以剑迎剑！
We'll meet sword with sword!
你们是异教徒！
You are pagans!
我们有更伟大的天主站在我们这边！
We have the greater God on our side!
基尔坦，我觉得该给这小子一个教训
Kjartan. I think we should teach this boy a lesson.
靠进去
(KJARTAN) Taking her in.
- 快跑！- 加快速度！
- At speed! - (MAN) Pick up the speed!
跟我回去！快走！去要塞！快跟上！
(MAN 1) Come back with me! Move it! (MAN 2) To the fort! Come on!
带上孩子！快走！
(MAN 3) Grab the children! Move!
你想问我为什么不守护村子
(LORD UHTRED) Why do I leave the villages unprotected
而是把人都撤进堡内？
and bring the men inside?
这是你想问的吗？
Is that your question?
村子烧了还能重建，战士死了就是死了
A village can be rebuilt, a warrior can die only once.
丹麦人可能正往南朝约克进发
The Danes may be heading south to Eofervvic,
但一路上碰到谁他们都会杀
but they will kill whoever they can on the way.
去把神父找来
Now, go and End the priest.
好的，父亲
(OSBERT) Yes, Father.
进来吧，奥斯伯特，别躲在阴暗处
(BEOCCA) Come in, Osbert, don't skulk in the shadows.
父亲让我来问您准备好了没
(OSBERT) He wants to know if you're ready.
快了
(BEOCCA) Almost.
你知道我在忙什么吗？
Do you know what I'm tasked with?
- 呃，写信？- 是回信，回的是这封信
- Um, a letter? - A response to a letter, this letter
埃拉国王来的信
from King Aella.
他请求你父亲出兵相助
Asking your father for his support, his army,
帮他夺回约克城
to help recapture the city of Eofervvic.
这就是为什么读书写字很重要
This is why it's important to read and write.
父亲不识字，也不会写
Father can't read nor write.
唉，你父亲这把年纪，学也学不了了
Yeah, well, for your father it's too late.
埃拉国王大可以派个人骑马来传话
King Aella could have sent a man on horseback.
骑马送信的人说的就一定是真话吗?
Who's to say the man on horseback speaks the truth?
或者他还记得原话吗?
Or has remembered the true message?
这些文字记录的是历史，是事实
What these letters will represent is history, facts.
你父亲正在通知埃拉国王和奥斯伯特国王
Your father is informing King Aella and King Osbert
他将与他们的军队一同在约克会师
he will be alongside their armies at Eoferwic.
贝班堡的印章便是这封信真实性的保证
And the mark of Bebbanburg will guarantee the truth of it.
我们为什么要为约克而战?
Why do we fight for Eofervvic?
我们为约克而战
Well, we fight for Eofervvic
是因为我们不想眼睁睁看着英格兰一块一块地落入丹麦人之地
because we do not wish to see England, piece by piece, become Daneland.
哈哈,我听说我们曾经也是异教徒
Heh, heh. I heard it said that we were pagans once,
说沃登和奥丁其实是同一个神
that Woden and Odin are the same.
我们认清了自己的错误,转而皈依罗马
We saw the error of our ways, looked to Rome.
我听说异教徒有凶猛的战争之神
I heard the pagans had fierce gods of war.
我们走的是正道,他们才是走错了路
Well, we are right and they are mistaken.
奥斯伯特,我们是蒙受祝福的人
Osbert, we are blessed.
我得让你对着圣卡斯伯特的梳子发誓
I should make you swear on St Cuthbert's comb
以后再也不许提沃登之类的名字
never to mention the likes of Woden again.
可要是我有一条狗叫沃登呢?
But what if I had a hound called Woden?
- 那你怎么办? - 要是你有头猪叫托尔呢?
- What would you do then? - What if you had a pig called Thor?
- 走吧，去见你父亲 - 一头叫托尔的猪
- Come. Let's go see your father. - A pig called Thor.
- 那真的是圣卡斯伯特的梳子吗? - 当然是圣卡斯伯特的梳子
- Is it really St Cuthbert's comb? - Of course it's St Cuthbert's comb,
他的圣发就留在那梳齿之间
and his holy hair lies in the teeth of that comb.
-你父亲人呢？- 他在跟侍女鬼混
- Where was your father last? - He was humping the servant girl.
- 胡说，奥斯伯特 - 我没胡说
- That's a lie,，Osbert. - No.
- 你就没打算消停吗? - 没有
- Are you never gonna tire of teasing? - Nope.
有骑兵来了!
(MAN) Horsemen approaching!
他骑的是乌特雷德的马
He rides Uhtred's horse.
奥斯伯特
(BEOCCA) Osbert.
不，不!
No. No!
把他剩下的身体埋了
Bury what's left of him.
奥斯伯特，走吧
(BEOCCA) Osbert, come on.
提醒我，我最后跟他说了什么
Remind me of the last words I spoke to him.
你让他只看，不许出战，我们...
You told him to watch and do not Tight. We have...
不许出战就是不许出战
Do not fight means do not fight.
- 他还年轻 - 到约克之前不许出战
- He was young. (LORD UHTRED) No fight until Eoferwic.
您要见奥斯伯特，大人
(BEOCCA) You wanted to see Osbert, my lord.
你
You.
你现在叫乌特雷德
You are now called Uhtred.
乌特雷德，乌特雷德之子，你带着那块石头了吗，那块琥珀?
Uhtred, son of Uhtred. You have your stone, the amber?
- 带了 - 神父会带你了解你的历史
- Yes. - The priest will show you your history,
- 那些羊皮卷，让他明白 - 大人，我...
- parchments. Make him understand. (BEOCCA) Lord, I...
我想再给他施一次洗礼
I should like to baptise him again.
若他以乌特雷德之名到达天堂之门
If he arrives at heaven's gate as Uhtred,
他们可能会纳闷奥斯伯特去哪儿了
they might wonder what's happened to Osbert.
你必须做的就做，但也照我说的办
Do what you must, but do as I ask.
遵命，大人
(BEOCCA) Lord.
孩子，我们曾经是这里的王，统治着
We were kings here once, boy. Kings of all the lands
- 图耶德河与泰恩河之间的所有土地 - 我们理应再度称王
- between rivers Tuede and Tine. - We should be kings again.
理应如此，但他们称我们什么不重要，只要他们服从就行
We should, but it does not matte,what they call us so long as they obey.
我们的祖先打下了这片土地
Our ancestors took this land.
这片土地是我们用血肉打下来的
It's been strengthened with our blood and bone.
你现在是贝班堡新的继承人，听到了吗？
And now you are the new heir of Bebbanburg. You hear me?
必要时，你要为它而死
And you will die for it if needed.
我会把杀了乌特雷德那个人的脑袋交给你
And I'll give you the head of the man who killed Uhtred.
不，你就是乌特雷德！
No, you are Uhtred!
你没在听我说话吗？
Have you not been listening to me?
别跟我说你要干什么，你还只是个毛头小子
Do not tell me what it is you will do, you are just a pup.
你什么都不用给我，你只要看，只要学
You will give me nothing. You will watch and you will learn.
在他母亲念叨我之前让他接受洗礼吧
Put him in the water before his mother's tongue gives me grief.
她不是我母亲
She's not my mother.
你会带他上战场去看去学吗？
Will you take him with you to battle to watch and learn?
我要你挑三十个人，留守贝班堡
I need you to choose 30 men and remain here at Bebbanburg.
保护这孩子，他是继承人
Protect the boy. He is the heir.
三十人守得住，粮食也够用，帮我做这件事？
Thirty will hold, few enough to feed. Do this for me?
我更想跟你一起去，但我会照你说的做
I'd rather be with you, but I'll do as you ask.
谢了
Thank you.
来，快点
(GLENNA) Come on, quickly.
上去，快走
Up there, go on.
快，快些
(BEOCCA) Hurry, please.
天父啊
(BEOCCA) Heavenly Father,
请接纳你的仆人乌特雷德
receive your servant, Uhtred,
让他进入圣徒的神圣国度
into the holy kind of saints
与最光明的天使同列
and into the ranks of the most bright angels.
愿你的圣水洗净他
Let your holy waters cleanse him
使他配得上你的祝福
and make and him worthy of your blessing,
让他成为你的器皿与权杖
make him your instrument and your rod.
让他领悟文字的力量
Let him realise the significance of the written word
好让他了解你的荣耀
so that he may learn of your glory
进而传播你的福音
and in turn may spread your word.
- 贝奥... - 让他在智慧中成长
- Beo.._ - Let him grow in wisdom
在敬畏中成长
and in respect
- 好让他以虔敬之道领导众人 - 贝奥...
- so he may lead in a godly manner. - Beo...
贝奥卡，他已受洗净了
Beocca, he's cleansed.
- 阿门
- Amen.
乌特雷德，贝班堡的乌特雷德之子，欢迎来到基督的世界
Uhtred, son of Uhtred of Bebbanburg, welcome to the Christian world.
看看你的子民和你的土地
Behold your people and your land.
人都去哪了，士兵们呢?
(UHTRED) Where are the people, the soldiers?
在去约克的路上，你父亲带领着他们
On the road to Eofervvic, led by your father,
去与另外两位国王会合
where they'll join the other two kings.
- 没带我? - 你要留在贝班堡
- Without me? - You are to remain at Bebbanburg
跟你叔父待在这儿，我负责保护你，要是想打架，就来跟我掰手腕
with your uncle. I'm to keep you safe. You wish to fight, we arm-wrestle.
- 神父呢? - 跟你父亲去了，吃东西吧
- Where's the priest? - With your father. Eat.
你要去马厩干活，乌特雷德
You have work to do, Uhtred, in the stables.
好在他们还给我们留了几匹马
Thankfully, we've been left some horses.
- 你该吃点东西 - 我不饿
- You should eat. - (UHTRED) I'm not hungry.
我们有活要干
(AELFRIC) We have work to do.
马粪要铲
Horse shit to shovel.
干完了来找我
Come and find me when you've finished.
斯卡利昂,
Scallion,
我兄弟如果战死，那孩子也必须死
if my brother falls in battle, the boy must fall.
走这么远，连个接风的人都没有
(EARL RAGNAR) All this way and no reception party.
拉格纳伯爵
(GUTHRUM) Earl Ragnar.
古斯鲁姆
(EARL RAGNAR) Guthrum.
- 你还好吗? - 好，就是饿了
- How are you? - I'm fine. I'm hungry.
- 你的孩子呢? - 快来了
- (GUTHRUM) And your boy? - He's coming.
拉格纳，我带来了人马
(UBBA) Ragnar. (EARL RAGNAR) I brought men, horses.
见到你真好，一切都好?
Good to see you. You well?
你把他儿子的头颅当礼物送给他?
You made a gift of his own son's head?
那位领主是什么反应?
How did this lord react?
他什么都没做
He did nothing.
他把手下的战士带进城堡,，待在里头不出来
He brought his warriors into the fortress, kept them inside.
- 那不是胆怯 - 是隐忍
- It was not cowardice. - (GUTHRUM) Restraint.
他在保存实力
He is saving his men.
此人就是乌特雷德
(UBBA) That man is Uhtred.
诺森布里亚三位国王之一
One of the three kings of Northumbria.
- 骁勇的战士国王 - 另外两个都是蠢货
- Warrior king. - (GUTHRUM) Other two are fools.
只顾着内斗
They'd rather be fighting each other.
- 此话当真? - 埃拉王和奥斯伯特王,
- This is true? - King Aella and King Osbert,
两人都争着要占约克
they both lay claim to Eofervvic.
- 他们的名字真是奇怪
- They have the strangest of names. - (CHUCKLES)
- 那我们什么时候开打? - 快了，但愿如此
- So when do we fight? - Soon, I hope.
我还没决定
I'm still to decide.
不管蠢不蠢，他们有三支军队
Fools or not, they have three armies.
- 他们确实人多 - 但各自为战
- They have numbers. - (EARL RAGNAR) But are divided.
三个国王，却只有一个能统领全局的人，就是这个乌特雷德
Three kings, but only one who can lead them. This Uhtred.
杀了他，整个诺森布里亚就是我们的
Kill him and Northumbria is ours, all of it.
听他说，听这小子说，他让我想起了年轻时的自己
Listen to him. Listen to the boy. He reminds me of me.
对，你年轻的时候，哈哈
Yeah, when you were younger. Heh, heh.
当然是年轻的时候
Of course when I was younger.
- 他不过是个孩子 - 随便说说
- He's just a boy. - Just saying.
- 乌巴… - 你是说我老了？斯托里
- (EARL RAGNAR) Ubba... - Did you say I was old? Storri.
- 没有 - 我没有老
- No. - (UBBA) I'm not getting old.
乌巴
Ubba.
我已经看过城外的地形了
I have seen the land outside the city.
我心里有个计划，是个好计划
I have a plan in mind, a good plan.
我儿子也想跟你们一起见见血
And my son would like to wet his sword with you.
那我们打不打？
So do we fight?
斯托里？
Storri?
征兆不错，就在今晨，我看见一只渡鸦
The signs are good. Only this morning, I saw a raven
朝撒克逊人的营地飞去，像是在召唤我跟上
fly towards the Saxon camp, and it was asking me to follow.
- 我确信如此 - 嗯
- I'm sure of it. - Mm.
- 那就开打 -
- Then we fight.
开打！
(MAN) We fight!
这是什么鬼地方？
(KING OSBERT) What kind of hell is this?
这是异教徒的地狱
(AELLA) it's a pagan's hell.
我们人数占优
We outnumber them.
还有更多人，一定有
There are more. There must be.
计划不变，先派一半人马出击
Nothing changes. We attack with half our number,
摸清他们的底细后，另一半跟进
second half to follow once we have the measure of them.
- 他们已经放弃了高地 - 埃拉王
- They have conceded higher ground. - (KING OSBERT) King Aella,
你和乌特雷德大人的军队率先发起冲锋
yours and Lord Uhtred's armies will attack in the first wave.
预备！预备！
(AELLA) Prepare! Prepare!
举盾!
Shield!
不，不，别撇下我
No. No, not without me.
天黑之前，我们就能扫清这帮瘟神,
Come nightfall, we'll be rid of this plague
然后清点我们该得的战利品!
and counting our share of the plunder!
我的盾牌
(AELLA) My shield.
杀光他们!
Kill them all!
盾墙撑住了
(AELLA) The wall is holding.
上！手压在盾牌下面，往前顶！顶！
(LORD UHTRED) Go! Hands below your shield and drive! Drive!
后退!
Ease.
(MAN) Ease!
后退!
Ease!
- 后退! - 前进!
- Ease! - (LORD UHTRED) Push!
继续前进！起效了!
Keep pushing! it's working!
把他们压垮!
Drive them!
他们撑不住了，还不了手，我们赢了，你看
They're tiring, can't fight back. We're winning, look.
我们赢了
(MAN) We're winning.
- 跟上! -
- Follow! - (MEN SHOUTING)
往前冲!
Drive on!
还不行! 还不行!
Not yet! Not yet!
天主啊，不
Dear God, no.
立盾墙!
Shield!
Wall!
仁慈无边的天主啊，不要让这一切发生
Dear God of infinite mercy, not this.
杀光他们!
Kill them all!
护腿! 护腿!
(LORD UHTRED) Legs! Legs!
保护你们的腿!
Protect your legs!
举起你的利剑
Lift up your sword
庇护这些以你之名浴血的英格兰战士
and spare these men of England who fight in your name.
让那些异教徒的心胆俱裂, 魂飞魄散
Let the heathens' hearts crumble and wither.
将你的神力赐予这些英格兰战士
Bestow your power upon these men of England,
让他们用恶鬼的血来荣耀你的圣名
so they can glorify your name with the blood of the devils.
此刻请垂怜我们，主啊
Have mercy now, Lord.
不要抛弃我们，不要抛弃英格兰
Do not forsake us. Do not forsake England.
跟我来! 跟我来!
(LORD UHTRED) Follow me! Follow me!
拿下他!
Take him!
收紧盾墙！收紧盾墙，拿下他！
(EARL RAGNAR) Close the shield wall! Close the wall and take him!
啊！
Unh! Unh.
不
No.
这小子像只黄蜂，哈哈
He's like a wasp. Ha, ha.
-可惜黄蜂没了刺  - 是啊
(EARL RAGNAR) Wasp has lost its sting. (RAGNAR) Yeah.
你确定他是撒克逊人？他打起来像个丹麦人
(RAGNAR) Are you sure he's a Saxon? He fights like a Dane.
是啊
(EARL RAGNAR) Yeah.
起来！
(MAN 2) Get up!
- 放开她
- (BRIDA SCREAMING) - (EARL RAGNAR) Leave her.
她得活着
She is to live.
这些年轻的，留着有用
Some of these young ones can come in useful.
父亲，这就是我跟你提过的那个男孩
Father, here's the boy I spoke of.
差点要了你命的那个？你就把他扔给我？
The one who almost killed you? You're leaving him with me?
我还从没见过谁能在你手里占到便宜
I've never seen a man get the better of you yet.
给我切点鸡肉
(RAVN) Cut me some chicken.
小心,刀刃很锋利
Careful, the blade is sharp.
能要人命的
It can kill a man.
鸡肉在你盘子里了
The chicken is on your platter.
你一直是瞎子吗?
Have you always been blind?
哦，我能看到不少
Oh, I see enough.
他们在下面杀的是什么人?
So who have they been killing below?
俘虏
(UHTRED) Prisoners.
刚才杀了个国王
Just now a king.
他死得英勇吗?
Did he die well?
- 没有 - 那他本就不配当国王
- No. - Then he shouldn't have been king.
告诉我,大厅正中坐的是谁?
Tell me, who sits in the middle of the hall?
是一个大块头和一个小个子吗?
Is it the big man and a small man?
是的，他们中间还坐着一个灰发男人
(UHTRED) Yes, and a grey man sits in between them.
如果你能活下去，就得提防那个大块头——乌巴
If you get to live, you should beware of the big man. Ubba.
我的忠告是，永远别惹乌巴
My advice for you is to never cross Ubba
而且永远，永远别跟他动手
and never, never fight him.
- 如果我能活下去? - 他只听众神的话
- If I get to live? - He listens to no one but the gods.
听命于众神的人，谁都摸不透他
Men who take their orders from the gods are unpredictable.
你说'如果我能活下去'
What did you mean
是什么意思?
when you said if I get to live?
你是我的俘虏
You're my prisoner.
那个灰发男人应该是埃格伯特
The grey man will be Egbert.
他是个撒克逊郡长
He's a Saxon ealdorman.
他已宣誓效忠，如今自称国王
He has pledged allegiance and now calls himself king.
他不过是个傀儡国王
He is king of nothing.
用不了多久，英格兰所有国王都将是傀儡国王
Soon all of the kings in England shall be kings of nothing.
诺森布里亚已归我们所有
Northumbria is ours.
麦西亚也快了
Mercia will soon by ours.
然后是东盎格利亚、康沃卢姆
Then East Anglia, Cornwalum,
以及最丰厚的奖励，就是威塞克斯，最后的王国
and then the greatest prize is the last kingdom, Wessex.
我听说过威塞克斯
I've heard of Wessex.
任何东西都能在威塞克斯的土地上生长
Anything will grow in Wessex.
告诉我你叫什么
(RAVN) Tell me your name.
乌特雷德
Uhtred.
我是贝班堡的郡长
I'm the ealdorman of Bebbanburg.
- 是吗? - 是的，我在北边有封地
- You are, huh? - I am. I own lands to the north.
你当这片土地的郡长多久了?
How long have you been an ealdorman of these lands?
你父亲选择跟我们开战
Your father chose to fight us
现在已经死了
and is now dead.
他……他不喜欢我
He... He was not fond of me.
我现在明白了，为什么我儿子要留你一命
I now understand why my son spared you,
贝班堡的乌特雷德
Uhtred of Bebbanburg.
你是个战士
You are a warrior.
来，喝点麦酒
Have some ale.
喝吧
Drink it.
多喝点
Lots of it.
拿去
Here.
搬上去
Take it up there.
我想把他们两个都留下，男孩和女孩
I'm thinking of keeping them both, the boy and the girl.
可以帮你母亲干活
Can help your mother.
- 有意见? - 没有
- Disagree? - No.
但我们毕竟杀了他父亲
But we did kill his father.
如果他是郡长，我们可以拿他换赎金
If he's an ealdorman, we could sell him for ransom.
也许吧
Perhaps.
布丽达，小心别把水洒了，地板会变成烂泥的
Brida, be careful not to spill the water. You'll turn the floor to mud.
乌特雷德，去劈柴
Uhtred, wood needs to be chopped.
布丽达，你去喂山羊
Brida, you can do the goats.
乌特雷德会有时间玩吗?
(THYRA) Will there be time for Uhtred to play?
干完活才能玩
Only when work is done.
我不喜欢咱们女儿跟奴隶一起玩
I don't like our daughter having to play with slaves.
- 他们只是孩子 - 各有各的位置
- They're only children. - They have a place.
暴脾气
Grumpy.
牵我的马来
(RAGNAR) My horse.
嘿, 拉格纳·拉格纳松
Hey, Ragnar Ragnarson.
嘿, 不知道哪儿来的乌特雷德
(RAGNAR) Hey, Uhtred of wherever.
你能教我用剑吗?
How about you teach me how to use a sword?
我们不教奴隶如何战斗
We don't teach slaves how to fight.
你那张嘴迟早会要了你的命，小子
That tongue of yours will be your death, boy.
现在，给我回去干活
Now, get back to work.
你们打算怎么玩?
What does the play involve?
我们在峡谷里建了一座大厅
We built a hall in the gorge.
我是女主人，乌特雷德是战士
I'm the mistress and Uhtred is a warrior.
不是仆人?
Not a servant?
这是个游戏
It is a game.
- 狼来了  - 乌特雷德
- A wolf! - Uhtred.
就是一头狼
(UHTRED) That's it, a wolf.
野猪，小心!
(BRIDA) Boar. Watch out!
我看见了，尖牙利齿，黄眼睛
(UHTRED) I saw it. Its sharp teeth and yellow eyes.
- 别让狼靠近我，乌特雷德 - 用火把它们赶走
- Don't let the wolves get to me, Uhtred. - Use the Ere to keep them away.
我看见它们了，跟乌巴一样壮，味道比他还难闻
I see them. They're as big as Ubba and smell worse.
你看见了吗?
Did you see that?
乌特雷德
Uhtred.
待在上面
Stay up there.
你看
Look.
乌特雷德，出什么事了? 待在上面，蒂拉
(THYRA) Uhtred, what is happening? (UHTRED) Stay up there, Thyra.
- 是斯文，他不会伤害你的 - 但他会杀了我们
- It's Sven, he won't hurt you. - (BRIDA) But he'll kill us.
他要杀我们! 快跑!
(BRIDA) He'll kill us! Run!
那是一把真剑
That was a real sword.
我看见了
(BRIDA) l saw it.
- 啊! 乌特雷德! - 蒂拉
- (THYRA) Ah! Uhtred! - Thyra.
乌特雷德!
(THYRA) umred!
脸怎么了？
(RAGNAR) whats this?
你又打架了?
You been fighting again?
- 是的 - 跟斯文打的?
- (UHTRED) Yes. - With Sven?
- 基尔坦的儿子? - 是的
- Kjartan's son? - (UHTRED) Yes.
- 乌特雷德，他比你大多了 - 他是个烂人
- Uhtred, he's much bigger than you. - He's a turd.
你干嘛这么说? 谁先动手的?
(SIGRID) Why do you say that? (RAVN) Who started it?
- 谁先动的手? - 是我先动的手
- Who began the fight? - (UHTRED) I began the fight.
就因为他是个烂人?
For no other reason than that he's a turd?
丹麦人为更小的事就杀人了
Danes have murdered for less.
乌特雷德，够了
(SIGRID) Uhtred, that's enough.
- 你想被卖掉吗，小子? - 我想吃饭
- You want to be sold, boy? - I wish to eat.
- 大声说 - 我想吃饭
- Speak up. - (UHTRED) I wish to eat.
你想吃饭?
You want to eat?
你知道吗
You know what?
要我说你就该饿着
I say you starve.
打架可以理解，不听话可不行
Fighting is expected, disobedience is not.
是斯文先动的手
- (SLAP AND UHTRED GRUNTS) -Sven began the fight.
基尔坦!
Kjartan!
拉格纳伯爵，请先听我说，他是个好孩子
Earl Ragnar, let me first say, he's a good boy.
他带着剑闯进我的地盘，我会跟他好好谈谈
He brought a sword onto my land. I will have words with him.
- 将来他会在你的船上效力 - 他冒犯了我
- In time, he'll serve on your ship. - He has offended me.
- 他会尊敬你的，他没有恶意 - 他没有恶意?
- He will honour you. He meant no harm. - He meant no harm?
他看了我女儿的裸体
He looked at my daughter's nakedness.
他受到惩罚了，你那撒克逊奴隶划伤了他
And he was punished. Your Saxon slave cut him.
这样我就要放过他吗？
(EARL RAGNAR) Shall I make a square of branches?
你是要为你儿子跟我打一架，还是把他叫出来?
Are you gonna fight me for your son or fetch him?
斯文，出来
Sven. Come out here.
- 把你要说的话告诉他 - 对不起
- Tell him what you have to say. - I'm sorry.
- 他听不到你说话 - 大人，对不起，我不该那样做
- He can't hear you. - I'm sorry, lord, for what I did.
你对我女儿动手动脚
You laid hands on my daughter.
你扒掉了她的衣服
You stripped her naked.
- 大人，只是脱了一半 - 大人，他这个年纪嘛
- Half-naked, lord. - He's at an age, lord.
是这样吗?
Is this true?
- 只脱了一半? - 是的,大人
- Half-naked? - Yes, lord.
那我就只挖他一只眼
Then I shall only take his one eye.
不要，大人，求你了
(KJARTAN) No, lord, please. (SVEN) Ah!
基尔坦，我将你驱逐出我的领地
(EARL RAGNAR) Kjartan, you are banished from my land.
我有样东西给你
I have something for you.
什么东西?
What is it?
一块护身符，托尔之锤
An amulet. Thor's hammer.
- 可是…… - 可是什么?
- But, uh... - But what?
你是基督徒
You're Christian.
拿着
Take it.
- 我不能拿 - 你不想要吗?
- I can't. - Don't you want it?
- 我想要 - 那就拿着
- I do want it. - Take it.
- 我在想办法拿 - 拿着
- I'm trying. - Take it.
- 我觉得他不想要 - 我想要
- (RAGNAR) I don't think he wants it. - I do want it.
不，我看不见得
(RAGNAR) No, I don't think so.
谢谢
Thank you.
跟我说说丹麦
Tell me about Denmark.
你的故乡
Your home.
丹麦嘛，能说什么
What can I say about Denmark?
潮湿
(RAGNAR) It's wet.
又苦寒
And harsh.
土地很平而且都是沙子，什么也种不出来
The ground is so flat and sandy, you can't grow a fart.
所以我们才来英格兰
Which is why we're here in England.
来扎根生息
To grow.
也是为什么小拉格纳不久后要去爱尔兰
And why young Ragnar will soon be going for Ireland.
你要走了?
(UHTRED) You leave to Tight?
为了财富
(RAGNAR) To make my wealth.
想要土地和银子，就得自己去抢
If you want land or silver, you have to take it.
今天你让我骄傲，乌特雷德
You made me proud today, Uhtred.
你真的让我骄傲
You made me proud.
我不认识你
(AELFRIC) I don't know you.
你看着不像信使
You don't have the appearance of a messenger,
- 乌巴的贡款也还没到期 - 不是的，大人
- and Ubba's payment's not yet due. - (KJARTAN) No, lord.
我是个船主
I was a ship's master.
我没有船, 也不需要船主
Well, I have no ships. I need no ship's master.
我有你想听的消息
I have news that you will want to hear.
- 说吧 - 我想要些回报，大人
- Well? - I would want something in return, lord.
不是现在，也不是钱
Not now, not coin.
但也许我们可以长期互相帮衬
But perhaps we can continue to help each other.
也许吧
Perhaps.
从这里往南走两天
Two days south of here
就到了拉格纳伯爵的地盘，我以前侍奉他
is Earl Ragnar, the man I used to serve
后来他把我驱逐出去
until he banished me.
他有个奴隶，他对这个奴隶很好
He has a slave, treats him well.
这个奴隶你有权赎回，如果你想的话
This is a slave you're entitled to buy back if you wish to.
- 赎回? - 大人，那是您的侄子乌特雷德
- Buy back? - It's your nephew Uhtred, lord.
他还活着
He lives.
要是我不想被赎回呢?
(UHTRED) What if I'm against being ransomed?
你的家人发现你还活着
Your family has discovered that you're still alive
他们想把你接回去
and they wish for you to be returned.
但他们得付钱
But they must pay.
- 付钱给拉格纳? - 乌巴要抽走一大半
- Pay Ragnar? - Ubba takes more than half.
这很正常
It's normal.
但我已经没有家人了
But I have no family.
让他们待在那边，把马拴好
(MAN) Keep them over there, tether the horses.
斯卡利昂，就是他
Scallion. Him.
乌特雷德
Uhtred.
他们待你好吗?
Are they treating you well?
- 有得吃，是的 - 好
- I am fed, yes. - Good.
好，那就好
Good, that's all we ask.
你脖子上挂的是什么，某种象征吗？
What is that around your neck, some symbol?
- 哦，这个? 他们让我戴的 - 我能看看吗?
- Oh, this? They make me wear it. - May I see it?
听着，我得和你说实话
(WHISPERS) Look, I will speak plainly.
你叔父会杀了你的
Your uncle will kill you.
明白吗? 你不能回贝班堡
Right? You cannot go back to Bebbanburg.
你必须逃走
You must escape.
他想当郡长，想当国王
He wants to be the ealdorman, wants to be king.
就像那边那个可怜虫埃格伯特一样
Like the pathetic Egbert over there.
给丹麦主子当傀儡国王，你该去威塞克斯
A puppet king for his Danish masters. You should go to Wessex.
去找真正的国王埃塞尔雷德和他的兄弟阿尔弗雷德王子
Seek out for that real King Aethelred and his brother the Prince Alfred,
他们是好人，虔诚的基督徒
they're good men, good Christian men.
你在他耳边说够了没有，神父
(EARL RAGNAR) That's enough whispering in his ear, priest.
- 乌特雷德 - 再多说一个字
- Uhtred. - One more word,
我就把你的蛋蛋割下来做成钱袋
I'll have your ball bag for a purse.
我在那儿等你 不必了
I'll meet you there. That will not be necessary.
他说什么了?
What did he say?
他... 他问你有没有好好待我
He... He asked if you were treating me well.
多少? 三百银币
(AELFRIC) How much? (RAVN) Three hundred.
你这是狮子大开口
(AELFRIC) That is a ridiculous amount.
一个孩子怎么可能值三百银币?
How can a boy be worth 300 pieces of silver?
因为我说了算，因为他是领主，是郡长
Because I say so, because he is a lord and an ealdorman.
不, 他只是个孩子
No, he is a boy.
我才是贝班堡的郡长，我掌着印章和旗帜
I am the ealdorman of Bebbanburg. I carry the seal and banner.
那印章是我父亲的，现在是我的
That seal is my father's, which is now mine.
给我闭嘴，你不过是待价而沽的货
You be silent. You are for sale, nothing more.
- 是赎金，大人 - 我就是这个意思
- For ransom, lord. - That's what I said.
各位大人，我已经献出了土地和马匹
My lords, I have given up land, horses.
还提供了大量粮食和我的剑
I've offered a generous supply of food as well as my sword.
我只求一个公道的价钱来换回我唯一的侄子
All I ask in return is a fair price for my only nephew.
你觉得什么价钱算公道?
(RAVN) What would you say is a fair price?
- 我出一百银币 - 两百银币
- I'll offer a hundred pieces of silver. - (RAVN) Two hundred.
我的效忠加上一百块银子，这价钱够公道了
My allegiance and 100 pieces is surely a fair price.
不够
(RAVN) It is not.
我出一百二十银币买这孩子
I will give 120 pieces of silver for the boy.
呵呵呵，不够
(RAVN) Heh, heh, heh. Not enough.
好吧
Very well.
两百块
Two hundred pieces.
我接受你的条件
I agree to your terms.
这孩子卖给拉格纳伯爵了
The boy is sold to Earl Ragnar.
- 什么? - 是赎回, 大人
- What? - (RAVN) Ransomed, lord.
我就是这个意思，此事已定
That is what I said. The matter is closed.
各位大人，我不远万里赶来，还献上了我的忠诚
My lords, I have come a long way. I have offered my allegiance.
所以你才能活到现在
Which is why you're allowed to breathe.
如果你有异议, 那就是对我有意见
If you have an argument, it's with me now.
事情谈完了的话
If business is done,
- 我们喝酒去 - 埃格伯特王该坐下歇歇了
- we have ale to drink. - (UBBA) And King Egbert needs to sit.
我不用被赎了吗?
(UHTRED) Am I not for ransom anymore?
你听到乌巴说的了，我把你买下来了
(EARL RAGNAR) You heard Ubba, I bought you.
我本来想把你献祭给奥丁
I thought I might sacrifice you to Odin.
你花了多少买我?
You bought me for how much?
- 太多了 - 多少叫太多?
- Too much. - How much is too much?
我那把剑等重的银子
My sword's weight in silver.
我承认我可能是吃亏了，但我们喜欢你，孩子
I agree I may have been robbed, but we like you, boy.
我们要留下你
We're going to keep you.
这是说我成丹麦人了?
(UHTRED) Does this mean I'm a Dane?
这是说你是乌特雷德·拉格纳松
It means you're Uhtred Ragnarson.
- 你现在是我的儿子了 - 啊!
- You are a son to me now. - Ah!
布丽达，不是那边，把山羊从旁边牵出去
Brida, not that way. Take the goat out the side.
下次，我保证
Next time, I promise.
- 母亲，你看 - 真美，真的很美
- Mother, look. - It's beautiful. It really is.
我不敢相信我就要失去你了
I can't believe I'm losing you already.
我就住在田地对面
I will be living across the field.
他要是待你不好，就穿过那片田走回来
If he doesn't treat you well, come marching back across that field.
哦，你看这地方
(UHTRED) Oh, look at this place.
乌特雷德，你喜欢我的婚礼项链吗?
Uhtred, do you like my wedding necklace?
喜欢，很漂亮
I do. Very pretty.
他懂什么项链
(RAVN) He doesn't know anything about necklaces.
还不如来问我
You might as well ask me.
乌特雷德，跟我来，帮我宰山羊
Uhtred, with me. You can help me slaughter the goats.
- 我刚洗完澡 - 哈哈
(UHTRED) I've only just washed. (EARL RAGNAR) Ha, ha.
山羊会高兴的
The goats will be pleased.
在那之后，你可以扫扫地
Later you can sweep the floor. Unh! Ha, ha, ha.
挪开
Move over.
找个借口聊聊，仅此而已
This is an excuse to talk, that's all.
蒂拉就要成亲了
With Thyra to be married,
也许是时候让你和布丽达定下来了
maybe it's time you got together with Bride.
有些男人，不错的男人，在打听她的事
There are men, good men, asking about her.
所以你得想清楚你对她算什么
So you have to decide what you are to her.
- 你们两个到底是什么关系 - 呵呵呵
- What you are to each other. - Heh, heh, heh.
- 布丽达有自己的主意 - 是啊
- Brida has her own mind. - She has.
但我看得出她看你的眼神
But I see the way she looks at you.
她今晚在林子里看守炭窑
She's watching the charcoal tonight in the woods.
骑我的马去找她
Take my horse and join her.
- 地上还暖着呢 - 哈哈哈
- The earth will be warm. - Heh, heh, heh.
为什么不呢
Why not?
我只是以为要成为真正的丹麦人，就得娶个丹麦女人
I just thought in order to be a real Dane, I had to marry a Dane.
去吧
Come on.
我疼你，就像疼小拉格纳一样
I love you like I love young Ragnar.
你在这儿干什么
What are you doing here?
你有没有想过你以前作为英格兰人的日子
Do you ever think of your English life?
在我们来到拉格纳这里之前，你是什么样的人
Who you were before we came to Ragnar?
没有
No.
你呢
Do you?
- 我想到我… - 嘘
- I think of who I... - Shh.
有声音
(BRIDA) Voices.
下面有人
Men below.
是丹麦人，他们是谁
Danes. Who are they?
那是基尔坦
That's Kjartan.
还记得他吗
Remember him?
那个一定是斯文
And that must be Sven.
不对劲，我们得去告诉拉格纳
This is wrong. We need to tell Ragnar.
他们挡在我们和大厅之间
They're between us and the hall.
那我们就绕路上去，把马留下，徒步跑过去
Then we go up and around. We leave the horses and run.
就在门前，对，就这样
(KJARTAN) In front of the door. That's it.
(DOG BARKING)
拉格纳，有烟
(RAVN) Ragnar, smoke.
着火了！蒂拉，快醒来！
Fire! Thyra, wake up!
都醒醒！快起来！
All them! Wake up!
着火了！
Fire!
快来 快点
(EARL RAGNAR) Come on! Come on!
这边走 拉文
(SIGRID) This way. Ravn.
- 救救我！- 来，快跟我来
(WOMAN) Help me! (SIGRID) Come. Come, quickly.
快来
Come.
- 这边门堵死了 - 这边也是
- The door is blocked. - So is this one.
做好准备
Be ready.
这边开着！这边开着，跟我来
(MAN) This one's open! This one's open. Come on, follow me.
这边走
(WOMAN) This way.
抓住孩子们
(KJARTAN) Take the children.
全抓走
Take them all.
弓箭手！
(KJARTAN) Archers!
别上去，等我
Don't go up there. Wait for me.
过来 过来
(SIGRID) Come. Come.
- 啊！- 拉格纳
- Unh! - (SIGRID) Ragnar.
关上门，蒂拉已经在我们手里了，其余的人就让他们烧死吧
Close the doors. We have Thyra. Let the rest burn.
带她一同去英灵殿
Take her with you to Valhalla.
好，我在那里等你
Yes. I will meet you there.
啊！
Argh!
不，不！
No. Oh, no.
找银子
Find the silver.
快！
Now!
他们在搜拉格纳的财宝
They're searching for Ragnar's wealth.
- 他们找不到的 - 去后面搜！
- They'll never find it. - (KJARTAN) Search in the back.
快点，我们马上就走
Come on, we're leaving soon.
你以为我离开了你，还娶了别人
You thought I'd left you, marry someone else.
但你知道
But do you know
我要对这副身子做些什么吗？
what I will do with this body?
对这张嘴？
This mouth?
我要把所有梦里想过的事都做一遍
I will do all I have dreamt of
还不止这些
and more.
谁又能阻止我？
And who will call a halt?
无畏伯爵拉格纳已死
Earl Ragnar the Fearless is gone.
跟他一起的，还有乌特雷德，他那条撒克逊宠物
And with him, Uhtred, his Saxon pet,
都化成灰了
a pile of ashes.
随便你
Anything.
- 嘘，蹲下 - 你看那个撒克逊人
- Shh. Get down. - Look at that man, the Saxon.
他叫斯卡利昂，是我叔父的手下
His name's Scallion. He works with my uncle.
- 他会去告诉叔父我已经死了 - 就让他去说吧
- He'll tell him that I'm dead. - Let him do it.
- 我看见他和基尔坦在一起 - 把这里烧成灰
- I see him with Kjartan. - (KJARTAN) Burn it to the ground.
也许他们在同流合污
(BRIDA) Maybe they're in it together.
他们凭什么以为这么做不会受到惩罚?
And what makes them believe they can do this without punishment?
嘘，他们会受到惩罚的，但不该出自你之手
Shh. They will be punished, but not by you.
乌特雷德，听我说，活着才是对拉格纳最好的交代
Uhtred, listen to me, we serve Ragnar best alive.
我们要把这件事说出去
We tell the story.
- 我要杀人 - 不行
- I need to kill someone. - No.
我选他
And I choose him.
乌特雷德，不行
Uhtred, no.
快点
(KJARTAN) Come on!
最主要的事情是把马都聚在这儿
(KJARTAN) The main thing is to keep the horses together here.
别把武器留在这里
Don't leave any weapons behind.
把那些搬过去，去后面看看
Move those over and we'll look in the back.
别留在里面，全都搬出来
Don't leave anything in there. Just bring it all out.
再来一点
(KJARTAN) A little bit more.
好 在这边！
(KJARTAN) Yeah. (MAN) Over here!
嘿，快点
(KJARTAN) Hey, come on.
你知道我是谁吗?
Yeah. You know who I am?
你找的就是我
It's me you're looking for.
你还记得我吗? 你还记得我吗?
You remember me? You remember me?
没有了
There's no more.
- 我们走 - 快点
- We're going. - (SVEN) Come on.
带上那些马
(KJARTAN) Bring the horses.
按理说这些该归小拉格纳的
By right it belongs to young Ragnar.
是的，但我们该花就花，先活下去
Yes. But we spend what we need to spend. We stay alive.
我们把实情告诉他人，然后呢
We tell the story and then what?
我们去投奔别的领主
We find a new lord to serve.
我不会袖手旁观，让属于我的东西被人夺走
I will not stand by and have everything that's mine taken from me.
我要回去
I'm going back.
去哪儿
Where?
回到起点
To the beginning.
- 是斯卡利昂吗？ - 不是，大人
- (AELFRIC) Is it Scallion? - No, my lord.
- 他看起来像个丹麦人 - 可能是基尔坦的手下
- He looks like a Dane. - Could be one of Kjartan's men.
我是贝班堡的乌特雷德，我要夺回属于我的一切！
I am Uhtred of Bebbanburg. I shall take what is mine!
贝班堡是我的！
Bebbanburg's mine!
备马
Horses.